<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The conspiracie of the wicked against the just. Laid open in a sermon preached at Eyke in Suffolk, Jan. 23. anno Dom. 1647. / By Zeph. Smyth. Preached and published, to set forth the grounds why the wicked lay such crimes to the charge of Gods people, as they are cleare of.</title>
            <author>Smyth, Zeph. (Zephaniah), fl. 1646-1648.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93436</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4361</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E467_8</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872312</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872312</idno>
            <idno type="VID">162306</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93436)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 162306)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 75:E467[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The conspiracie of the wicked against the just. Laid open in a sermon preached at Eyke in Suffolk, Jan. 23. anno Dom. 1647. / By Zeph. Smyth. Preached and published, to set forth the grounds why the wicked lay such crimes to the charge of Gods people, as they are cleare of.</title>
                  <author>Smyth, Zeph. (Zephaniah), fl. 1646-1648.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 15, [1], 19-30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Forcet for Iohn Rothwell, living in Pauls-Church-yard, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Sun and Fountaine,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the yeare, 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>B4 is canceled.</note>
                  <note>"The skillful teacher" has separate dated title page on C1v; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:162306:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE <hi>Conſpiracie of the Wicked against the Just.</hi> LAID OPEN IN A SERMON PREACHED At <hi>Eyke</hi> in <hi>Suffolk, Jan.</hi> 23. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1647.</p>
                  <p>BY ZEPH. SMYTH.</p>
                  <p>Preached and publiſhed, to ſet forth the grounds why the wicked lay ſuch Crimes to the charge of Gods people, as they are cleare of.</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>And they ſaid,</hi> Come let us imagine ſome device againſt <hi>Jeremiah;</hi> for Law ſhall not periſh from the Prieſt, nor Counſell from the wiſe, nor the word from the Prophet; Come, Let us ſmite him with the tongue, <bibl>
                        <hi>Jer. 18.12.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>And alſo they being idle, they learne to goe about from houſe to houſe, yea, they are not onely idle, but pratlers and buſie bodies, ſpeaking things which are not comely, <bibl>
                        <hi>1. Tim. 5.13.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>For they incourage themſelves in a wicked purpoſe, they commune of laying ſnares privily, and ſay who ſhall ſee them; they ſearch out Iniquities, they accompliſh a diligent ſearch, the inward thought of every one of them and the heart is deep; but God will ſhoot an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row at them ſuddainly, their ſtroke ſhall be at once: they ſhall cauſe their owne tongues to fall upon them. <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal. 64.5, 6, 7, 8.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed by THO: FORCET for <hi>Iohn Rothwell,</hi> living in <hi>Pauls-Church-yard,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the Sun and Fountaine, in the yeare, 1648.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:162306:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:162306:2"/>
                  <head>To all the Orthodox Chriſtians, that are followers of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt in ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, of the Towne of <hi>Wickam-Market,</hi> in <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk;</hi> ZEPH: SMYTH wiſhes the increaſe of grace here, and the fruition of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hereafter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Riends, the moſt wiſe God, who knowes what is beſt for his people, hath ſo ordered, that his people ſhall undergoe bad report as well as good: for the Diſciple is not above his Maſter, nor the Members above the Head; It was the Portion of Ieſus Chriſt, and therefore well may befall his followers; I he wicked will watch for occaſions againſt the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make them odious; hoping to juſtifie themſelves by charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others with ſuch crimes, as they are guilty of themſelves. If they have any juſt occaſion given them, through the fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of any of Gods people, or the diſcovery of any falſe heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Hypocrite, How do they joy at it; If they have not juſt occaſion: they will charge them with things that they are cleare of; The grounds why they doe it, you may pleaſe to reade in the enſuing Sermon; which though I have paſſed the bounds of modeſtie, to make thus publike in theſe Times, in
<pb facs="tcp:162306:3"/>which the ſtomacks of men are ſo full, that they loath the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney-combe, and the word of the Lord as a reproach and deriſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on daily; yet I have divers Reaſons for it, which I crave leave to conceale; Sure I am, it is a Doctrine ſutable to the times, to be both Preached and printed; It concernes that ſinne which cries to Heaven for vengeance; and is a great cauſe of our Lands trouble; It is true, I have put it forth unpoliſhed, as it was delivered unto a plaine Auditorie; and though not ſo large as it was delivered publiquely; yet here is the ſumme of it in briefe; if any in the peruſing of it expect high ſtraines, and ſtrong lines, and the words which man's wiſedome teaches, for ſuch I have laboured in vaine; If it find hard entertainment amongſt them which have curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pallets; If I ſhould pleaſe men, I were not the ſervant of Chriſt; if it bee hated amongſt lyars and ſlanderours, it is no wonder; <hi>For he that doth evill hateth the light, Ioh. 3.20.</hi> If any miſlike Ieſus Chriſt or his followers the worſe, becauſe they are reproached in the world; Such as refuſe Chriſt Ieſus, becauſe of a face buffetted and ſpit upon, may want of a Saviour and periſh miſerable; <hi>For all that will live godly in Chriſt Ieſus muſt ſuffer perſecution, 2 Tim. 3.12. And through many tribulations enter into the Kingdome of God.</hi> But if this plaine Sermon may but learne any poore ſoule a piece of Heaven, even any thing of the good old way I am ſatisfied; I commit the ſucceſſe to God, and preſent theſe lines to you, with my earneſt deſire and prayer to God for you, that you may be ſaved, though the weakeſt, and moſt unworthy of all the ſervants of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>ZEPH. SMYTH.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:162306:3"/>
                  <head>The Malignants Plot. OR, The Conſpiracy of the Wicked againſt the Juſt.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>PSAL. 35. part 11.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>They layd to my Charge things that I knew not.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Pſalme was a Pſalme of <hi>David</hi> whom though hee were a man according to Gods owne heart and walked cloſe with God; yet hee was a man of much troubles in this life and oft in great dangers; and as Gods providence doth not free his People from trouble but preſerves them in all their troubles; ſo did God preſerve this ſervant of his in the midſt of all his troubles; and as God will be ſought for that which he promiſeth unto his people; ſo the Prophet <hi>David</hi> doth not in his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſit ſtill and neglect the uſe of the meanes, ſaying, GOD hath promiſed deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance and hee will deliver whether I uſe the meanes or no; but the Prophet uſes the meanes, hee ſeekes unto God in his troubles; the Prophet was in great ſtraites at this time when he put up this Prayer unto God, expreſt in this Pſalme, by reaſon of <hi>Saul</hi> and all that tooke part with him, did furiouſly perſecute <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> digging Pits and laying ſnares for him without a cauſe; and the Prophet in this Pſalme makes his cauſe knowne to God intreating the Lord to plead his Cauſe and let his enemies fall into the Pit they digged for him.</p>
                  <p>And the Prophet in making his mone to God, complaines to God of their Cruelty in ſeeking his woe by bearing falſe witneſſe againſt him, as doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the Text, Falſe witneſſes did riſe up againſt mee <hi>they layd to my charge thinge that J knew not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:162306:4"/>
                  <p>Whether we read the words, They asked of mee things I knew not; or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the tranſlation, They layd to my charge, it beares all one ſence, and therefore I intend not to ſpend time about that but haſten to the matter — The words beare this ſence, <hi>Davids</hi> enemies did out of cruelty and malice againſt him intending him miſchiefe, charge him with ſuch things as hee never did, things that he was cleare of; the words then holding forth a Crime charged upon the Prophet they afford theſe Conſiderations; Firſt, the perſon charged with the Crime, <hi>David.</hi> Secondly, the perſons charging him, Cruell witneſſes, falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. Thirdly, the Crime, though it is not ſpecified what things in particular but in generall, things which imply ſeverall though ſuch things as they thought to have prevailed with againſt <hi>David.</hi> Fourthly, <hi>Davids</hi> innocency, <hi>things that I knew not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>My Doctrine I intend to inſiſt upon from the words for the preſent, is this;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> That it is many times the portion of the godly in this life to have ſuch Crimes layd to their charge by their Enemies as they are cleere of.</p>
                  <p>My method in handling of the Doctrine, God aſſiſting, ſhall be this. Firſt, to prove the truth of the Doctrine by Scripture. Secondly, to ſhew you the grounds from whence it ariſes. Thirdly, why God doth permit it; and fourthly, make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</p>
                  <p>The truth of the Doctrine you ſee plaine in the Text, and as in the text ſo the Prophet hath many expreſſions to this purpoſe in the Pſalmes, ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41. Fifthly, my enemies ſpeake evill of mee, ſaying, <hi>When ſhall be dye and his name periſh, Davids</hi> enemies were ſo bitter againſt him, that they ſpake evill of him with the tongue, and nothing would ſatisfie them but his life; when ſhall hee dye end his name periſh. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 6. If hee come to ſpeake with me he flatters but in his heart, he heapoth Iniquity, and when he comes abroad hee tells it forth; when they come to the Prophet, then they flatter as if they would comfort him and bemono his Condition; but hated him in the heart, and looke what they in their hearts did imagine of the Prophet that they tell abroad for truth; ſo ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.3. They compaſſed mee about, ſaith the Prophet, with words of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and fought againſt me without a Cauſe, what words were theſe living words as appeare, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. There was malice in the heart and it vented at the Tongue; when their is malice in the heart of a Man or Woman, then they plot which way to make their neighbour odious, though without cauſe; And as this was <hi>Davids</hi> Portion, ſo it was <hi>Jobs</hi> alſo when his three Friends came to comfort him, in ſtead of Comforting of him, they Iudge him and Charge him of that which hee was cleare of, as <hi>Iob</hi> 22.5. <hi>Is not thine Iniquity great,</hi> ſay they, as if they ſhould have ſaid, Thou are a great ſinner and now God hath met with thee, it is thy Sinne have brought this upon thee and now God layes open thy hypocriſie, But they Charged him falſly, for God did it to him; and as it was <hi>Iobs</hi> Portion, ſo <hi>Ieremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> goes not Scot-free, ſo <hi>Ierem.</hi> 18.18. Then they ſayd, come let us imagine ſome device againſt <hi>Jeremiah.</hi> The Lord by the Prophet prefigures the ruine of the People, under the parable of the Potters broken veſſell; and the Lord threatens to depopulate them, and to take away his Ordinances from them, if they did perſiſt in doing evill in his ſight; They were ſo miraged againſt the Prophet for this, that they are reſolved they will bee reveaged on him; then ſayd they, Come
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:162306:4"/>let us imagine ſome device againſt <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> for the law ſhall not periſh from the Prieſt, nor counſell from the Wiſe, nor the Word from the Prophet, Come let us ſmite him with the tongue, and let us not give heed unto any of his words; as if they ſhould have ſaid, What does hee threaten us, Come we will make him as bad as wee are, let us ſlander him, let us falſly accuſe him, wee are men of credit, and ſhall be beleeved whatſoever we ſay of him, let us ſmite him with the Tongue, and what followed you may find in Chapter the 20th. And it hath not onely been the Saints portion to have ſuch things layd to their Charge as they are cleare of; but it befell our Saviour Chriſt when hee was here upon earth, in <hi>Matth</hi> 8. in <hi>verſe</hi> 3. He was called a Blaſphemer in <hi>verſe</hi> 11. He was called a friend of Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans and Sinners, and in <hi>verſe</hi> 34. Hee was called a Conjurer; and if the head doe not eſcape what can the members goe free, no the Diſciple ſaith CHRIST is not above his Maſter, did they not call <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> a Divell, <hi>Math.</hi> 11.18. I pray ſee what the Apoſtle ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.8. Wee ſaith the Apoſtle approve our ſelves to be the Miniſters of Ieſus Chriſt by honour and diſhonour, by euill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and good report, as deceivers and yet true; in patiently bearing bad report as well as good report, which ſhew it is the portion of the godly Miniſters as well as People to undergoe bad report as well as good, you ſee the truth of the Doctrine is cleare to mee in the next place to ſhew you from what grounds this ariſe, that the Enemies of the godly ſhould <hi>Charge them with things they are cleare of.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> It ariſes from the godly mans avoyding the way of the Wicked; becauſe others are not as bad as themſelves and walke in the ſame way of Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that they themſelves doe walke in, therefore they are offended at them; this you may ſee 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.4. They thinke it ſtrange ſaith the Apoſtle, that yee manne not with them to the ſame exceſſe of Riot; therefore ſpeake they evill of you, that is the ground from whence it ariſet; it is a wonder to them, they thinke it ſtrange, as if they ſhould ſay, What ſhall none be ſaved but ſuch as pray, and read and run after Sermons, and are ſo exact in their lives as ſuch and ſuch are; What not allow us now and then to ſweare an Oath, now and then to tell a lye, now and then to be Drunke, now and then to play the good fellow; nay are they ſo ſtricke wee will ſmite them with the Tongue; wee are reſolved we will make them more odious then they make us; and the ground of it is, becauſe they have the way of a godly man. The Prophet <hi>Davids</hi> expreſſion is, They that reward mee evill for good are my Adverſaries; becauſe I follow goodneſſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.20. That it the ground whence it ariſes, becauſe I follow goodneſſe the wicked doth not ſo much hate the ſinne that they ſee in a godly man; for they will approve of the ſame ſinne in their Companions; but they are glad if they ſee any miſdemeanour in a child of God that they might reproach them, becauſe they labour after that which it good. And hence it comes to paſſe, if they ſee no juſt cauſe why they ſhould reproach a child of God, that they will invent ſomething againſt them; their hearts are ſo bitter againſt that of God that they ſee in them.</p>
                  <p>A ſecond ground from whence it ariſes, it the Hipocrifie in the heart; there is ſo much hypocriſie in the hearts of men and women, that they thinke all is well with themſelves, they have no need of Repentance of Reformation of life, they are good Men and Women, and have hearts as good as the beſt; like the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes,</hi>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:162306:5"/>juſtifie themſelves before men, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.15. but they are ſoone ready to judge others, to be very wicked and in a bad caſe; The ground of their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and condemning of others is the hypocrifie, in their hearts they judge not themſelves; the <hi>Phariſee</hi> had a good opinion of themſelves, and therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned Chriſt and his Apoſtles; this is the Reaſon why people many times ſpic a fault in another, it may be where none is, becauſe they cannot ſpie out their owne, as our Saviour Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.11. Why ſeeſt thou a moate in thy brothers eye and perceiveſt not a beame in thy owne; for truly if people would ſearch at home, they would not be ſo ready to condemne others and juſtifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
                  <p>A third ground from whence it ariſes, is the malice and envie in the hearts of people againſt the godly, if envie be in the hearts of men, unleſſe God quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them with grace it will vent out; <hi>Saul</hi> envied <hi>David,</hi> and ſee what plotting there was againſt him, how was <hi>David</hi> hunted up and downe from place to place; the <hi>Phariſces</hi> envied Chriſt, and ſee how it breaks out into action, how did they reproach him, and how oft did they ſeeke occaſion againſt him; the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill after he was fallen did envie mans happineſſe, and never left tempting till he had deſtroyed the whole race of Mankind; the envious man is not ſatisfied, unleſſe he ſee his neighbour fall, the <hi>Iewes</hi> envied the Prophet, <hi>Ier.</hi> 18.18. and they ſay, Come let us ſmite him with the tongue; hence it comes to paſſe, if the Miniſter of the word touch the Conſcience of a naturall man, and touch where it is galled a little, the envie in the mans heart will breake out one way or other.</p>
                  <p>A fourth ground from whence it ariſes, is their judging of the godly to be as bad as themſelves, there is many in the world like the Devill, meaſures every bodies corne by their owne buſhell. You may remember in the firſt of <hi>Iob,</hi> when the Lord ſaid unto Satan, haſt thou not conſidered my ſervant <hi>Iob,</hi> there is none like him on the earth, a juſt and upright man, one that feareth God and eſcheweth evill; ſayes Satan: What doth <hi>Iob</hi> feare God for nought, haſt not thou bleſſed him with ſubſtance, but touch his body and goods and ſee then if hee blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme thee not to thy face, the Devill knew he was ſo wicked that he would have done it; and he judges <hi>Iob</hi> to be as bad as himſelfe; <hi>Saul</hi> hee did envie <hi>David</hi> in his heart and ſought his life, and he judged the ſame of <hi>David,</hi> called him his enemy, and thought he had ſought his life; for many in the world are ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lde, that if they have occaſions of ſinne offered they doe not reſiſt, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring other folks cloath by their owne yard, they thinke others will doe ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; hence it comes to paſſe, that thoſe that are Adulterers and Fornicators themſelves, will ſooneſt charge others with it, that are cleare of it, and moſt commonly they that are moſt ſuſpicious of the chaſtity of others are naught them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, this is one ground of the wickeds <hi>charging of the godly with ſuch things as they are cleare of,</hi> their judging others to be as bad as themſelves.</p>
                  <p>A fifth ground from whence it ariſes, is the godlies refuſing to conſent to doe thoſe wicked actions, to which the wicked tempt them, this wee may ſee in <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph, Gen.</hi> 49. 7th. <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> Miſtris intices him to commit filthineſſe with her, in the 8th. verſe, wee have <hi>Ioſephs</hi> refuſall, alleadging this reaſon, How can I doe this great wickedneſſe, and ſo ſinne againſt God, a gracious expreſſion, and without
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:162306:5"/>all queſtion this <hi>Ioſeph</hi> had the feare of God before his eyes, but what did follow, you may ſee in the following part of the Chapter, ſhee would violently have ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to commit wickedneſſe with her, gat hold of his garment; but he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the feare of God before his eyes refuſed, and becauſe hee would not fulfill her wicked deſires, ſhe tells her husband, that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> came in to lye with her, and ſhee lift up her voyce and then he fled and got him out; ſhe charged him with that which hee was cleare of becauſe he did not doe the wicked act to which ſhe tempted him; ſo the wicked charge the godly many times with ſuch crimes as they are cleare of, becauſe they conſent not to doe that to which they are tempted; hence it comes to paſſe, if a man refuſe to be drunke with a company of drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, they out of malice will be ready to charge him with drunkenneſſe; ſo if hee refuſe bad company, and frequent the company of the godly, they will be ready either to charge him with keeping bad company, or gibe at him for holineſſe, onely upon this ground the not conſenting to thoſe wicked actions to which they are tempted.</p>
                  <p>A ſixth ground from whence it ariſes, is the deſire of wicked perſons to have it ſo, the wicked joy at the falles of Gods people, and they deſire ſuch occaſions to triumph over them; <hi>Let them not</hi> ſaith the Prophet, ah ſo would wee have it, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 35.25. What would they have they would have occaſion to rejoyce over him, they would have had that true which they did falſly charge the Prophet with in the Text; the wicked when they falſly accuſe the godly, they ſhew what they would have; and out of their deſire to have it ſo they watch the ſteps of the juſt; the wicked watcheth the juſt and ſeeketh to ſlay him, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 37.32. That is the end why they watch the ſteps of the juſt, that if it be poſſible they might ſlay him, and therefore the Prophet prayes, verſe the 19. of this 35. <hi>Pſalme.</hi> Let not them that are my enemies unjuſtly rejoyce over mee; Let them not joy over me, as if I were guilty of that which they charge me with; It implies that the wicked will joy if they have occaſion given them; and they are ſo impudent that they will rejoyce without alſo, as if they had a cauſe given them; therefore it much behooves a gracious ſpirit to walke ſo exact, as the wicked may not have juſt occaſion to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce over them; and to deſire of God ſo to direct them in his way, as they might not occaſion the wicked to triumph, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.12. ſaith the Prophet, They that intend mee evill talke wicked things and imagine deceit continually, and in verſe the 16. Heare me ſpeedily leaſt they rejoyce over mee; for when my foot ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth they magnifie themſelves, as if they had ſaid, Lord if thou now doeſt delay to help, then my enemies will triumph as if thou haddeſt forſaken mee; for it is their joy, if they ſee me halt, and to this purpoſe the Prophet prayes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127. verſe 11th. Teach me thy way oh Lord, and lead mee in a right path; becauſe of my obſervers, who were thoſe obſervers the Prophets enemies, ſuch as <hi>charged him with ſuch things as he knew not,</hi> as verſe 12. give mee not unto the luſts of my adverſaries, for there are falſe witneſſes riſen up againſt me, and ſuch as ſpeake cruelly. And truly Gods people had neede pray with <hi>David,</hi> That God would lead them in a right path; for the wicked joy if they doe ſtumble, and if they doe not ſtumble and give offence; then becauſe they would have it ſo they will beare falſe witneſſe againſt them, as if they ſhould ſay, wee would have it thus, come let us tell it for a truth, whether it be ſo or no; ſo that you ſee one
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:162306:6"/>ground from whence it ariſes, that the godly are charged with things which they know not is the deſire of the wicked to have it ſo.</p>
                  <p>A ſeventh ground whence it ariſes, is the malice of Satan againſt the godly, hee will falſly accuſe the godly himſelfe, and he hath not lived five thouſand and odde yeares for nothing, but that by this time, nay long agoe he taught his ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers ſome of his cunning; and they through the corruption of their hearts are ſo tractable to learne the Devils art, that they are very exact in this piece of ſervice to accuſe the godly, <hi>and charge them with things that they knew not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A eighth ground from whence it ariſes, is raſh judgement, the wicked judge all to be as bad as ſome, and hence it comes to paſſe if a profeſſor fall into a ſinne, they are ready to ſay of all that profeſſe Chriſt they are all alike; when <hi>David</hi> fell, the enemies of God blaſphemed not that wicked people hate the ſinne, for they can allow the ſame ſinne in themſelves they condemne in others; but they are enemies to true Religion, and are glad of any occaſion to ſpeake againſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſaying, this is your Religion and this is your profeſſion; but let mee tell ſuch thus much, that religion that teach men to be wicked is naught, and to bee cryed downe; and in ſome cauſes a man may juſtly charge the failings of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upon their religion, as to inſtance, if I ſee a <hi>Antinomian</hi> that denies the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Law to be a rule of life to a believer, ſweare, lye, ſlander, neglect holy duties, I may juſtly ſay to ſuch, this is your Religion; for if they take away that Law that forbids ſwearing, and lying, falſe witneſſe bearing, and command the true worſhip of God; then by what Rule ſhall ſuch people lead their lives; for it is true, the Law is ended to a believer, as a Covenant of workes to ſeeke righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and ſalvation by the doing of it; but it is not endad as a rule of directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the well ordering of our lives; ſo that when ſuch as deny the Law to be a Rule of life live contrary to the Law; I may juſtly ſay ſuch a religion, ſuch acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and thus I might inſtance concerning divers other Religions; but when a mans religion teaches him nothing but holineſſe, to give himſelfe onely to God, and crie downe all appearance whatſoever, if ſuch a one fall into ſinne take heed of charging it upon his religion, for God will not put it up at thy hands; <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.23. I will ſanctifie my great name amongſt the heathen whom yee have pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted; The heathen charged all the wickedneſſe they ſee amongſt the <hi>Iewes</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their God and religion; as if they ſhould have ſaid, I warrant they have a good God, and a good religion that they are ſo wicked; well ſaith the Lord, are yee ſo ready to charge all upon mee, and upon religion, I will be even with you, I will before I have done with you make you to know I am the Lord, and that religion teach my people no ſuch things; ſo ſay I, you that charge all the falles of profeſſors upon God and upon religion, God will be even with you; and hee will make you know before he have done with you, that the fault is to be charged upon the wickedneſſe in their hearts and not upon religion; — Suppoſe God doth now or then diſcover a hypocrite, or now and then let a deare child of his fall into a ſinne, this is not a ſufficient argument to fall upon religion, and ſay, who would be of ſuch a religion, except their religion doe allow them in ſuch acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; then wee muſt know that all that profeſſe religion are not truely religious; for there are many that preach Chriſt, and profeſſe Chriſt, that Ieſus Chriſt will not owne at the laſt day, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1. The ſtony ground made glorious ſhewes,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:162306:6"/>and yet came to nothing, <hi>Math.</hi> 13. And many ſaith Chriſt ſhall ſeeke to enter in and ſhall not be able, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.24. therefore the backſlidings of ſome and falls of ſome is no argument to prove all are ſuch; for there are ſome God will keep by his power through faith to ſalvation, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Objection.</hi> But you will ſay why does God permit wicked people to lay to the charge of the godly ſuch things as they are cleere of, God if hee pleaſed he could prevent it, and ſtop the mouthes of the wicked; that they ſhould not be able to ſpeake againſt his children.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> As all things worke for the beſt to them that love God, ſo this works for the good of Gods people; God doth permit it for the good of his people, and thus he fruſtrates the hopes of the wicked, they intend evill againſt the godly, and God diſpoſes of it for good; as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſaid to his brethren, you intended evill againſt mee and God diſpoſed of it for good; So may wee ſay to ſuch as falſly ſlander Gods people, you intended evill againſt the people of God, but God diſpoſes of it for good; there is a five fold good that God brings out of it to his people.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Firſt, God doth by this meanes humble them, and brings them to examine what is amiſſe; ſo that though they be cleare of that crime laid to their charge, yet they will then examine whether there be nothing elſe amiſſe betwixt God and them, they will ſearch their hearts and walke more humble, and cleave more cloſe to the Lord.</item>
                     <item>Secondly, God doth by this meanes bring tthem the oftner upon their knees, to ſeeke unto him, to plead their cauſe, and to cleare their innocency; how oft did the Prophet ſeeke unto God when the wicked did falſly accuſe him; how doe hee make his moane at the throne of grace unto God, beſeeching him to plead his cauſe; and to keep him cloſe in his way, that the wicked might not rejoyce at his downefall; ſo when Gods people ſees that it is that which the wicked would have; that which is their joy to ſee the godly fall into ſuch and ſuch a ſinne; then the godly will pray more earneſtly with <hi>David,</hi> Lord lead mee in a right path becauſe of my obſervers; then they will be earneſt with God to keep them from falſing into that ſinne that the wicked deſire they might fall into, and this is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond good that comes of it.</item>
                     <item>Thirdly, God doth uſe the teproach of the wicked as a preventing medicine againſt that crime which the wicked lay to their charge, the godly have unrenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nature as well as renued, and if God ſhould leave them never ſo little to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they are not their owne keepers, they might fall into that ſinne which the wicked layes to their charge, and every godly man and woman may ſay when they are falſly accuſed, it is Gods mercy that I did not fall into that ſinne they lay to their charge; had God left me to my ſelfe I might have beene guilty of that crime they lay to my charge; and God doth uſe wicked peoples tongues as a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning againſt ſuch a ſinne; that when they ſee how the wicked joy at a brat of their owne hatching; then they conſider, if the wicked thus joy without a cauſe, what would they doe if they had juſt cauſe; well, by the help of God this ſhall bee a warning to mee for ever to watch againſt that ſinne; for the time to come I will pray more againſt that particular ſinne then I have done, and watch more againſt that ſinne then I have done, through Gods help they ſhall never have occaſion
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:162306:7"/>to rejoyce over me in that kind; truly I verily believe many a child of God can ſay by experience, I ſhould never have prayed and watched againſt ſuch a ſinne ſo much, had not God uſed the tongues of the wicked as preventing Phyſick; I know not my owne heart, but that I might have fallen into ſuch and ſuch a finne, had not God by this meanes hedged up my way with thornes, and this is a third good comes of it.</item>
                     <item>Fourthly, God doth by this meanes exerciſe the graces in his people by letting them undergoe bad report as well as good report; hee tries whether they will cleave cloſe to him in all conditions, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.15, 16, 17. Confuſion is daily before mee, ſhame hath covered my face for the voice of the ſlanderer and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buker, though all this is come upon us, yet have wee not forgotten thee, not dealt falſly concerning thy Covenants.</item>
                     <item>Fifthly, God doth by this meanes teach them how to judge of others, when they are falſly accuſed for the time to come, they will not receive a falſe report againſt their neighbour, they will know the truth of a thing before they believe it, and they know how to comfort others in the like condition; and thus God diſpoſes of it for good, and thus God makes the wicked the ſervants of his people, in that very thing which the wicked thinke to wrong them moſt in; for hee uſes the wicked as the rod and wiſp, to ſcoure off the ruſt of their graces, and to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect their ſecuritie, and when the rod hath done its office then it is throwne into the fire; and thus you ſee how God diſpoſes of the wickeds falſe accuſations of his people for good.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> It then informes us, that it is no new thing for the people of God to be falſly accuſed; It was the device of the Devil! long agoe to accuſe falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as ſoone as there was a World, and man was created and placed in Paradiſe, he accuſes God to man by poſſeſſing our firſt parents, that God had not dealt well with them in denying them to cate of the tree of Knowledge, of good and evill; and truly the devill hath not lived five thouſand and odde hundred yeares for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; but the ſame devill that at firſt accuſed God to man can doe ſo ſtill, and if hee will accuſe God falſly, no marvell if hee teach his ſchollers to accuſe Gods people falſly; Wee find it was <hi>Davids</hi> portion, Chriſts portion, the Apoſtles portion; and what doe you thinke as the devill growes old hee growes childiſh, and forgets how to teach his ſchollers the ſame leſſons now hee did a great while a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe; no ſurely, as falſe accuſations have been the portion of Gods people for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſo it may be ſtill, and therefore if ſuch a thing happen, let not Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple carrie themſelves ſo, as if ſome ſtrange thing happened to them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> It informes us what deſperate wickedneſſe and malice is in the hearts of wicked people againſt the godly, which appeares by their deſire to rejoyce over the godly for their infirmiries, they watch for occaſions, and if they cannot finde occaſion, then they will invent ſomething againſt them; charging them with things which <hi>they knew not,</hi> but I leave this and come to a uſe of inſtruction, which concerne both the accuſer and accuſed.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, if it be ſo that Gods people may be falſly accuſed, this ſhould teach the people of God theſe leſſons; firſt, take heed that yee give not the wicked juſt occaſion to rejoyce by not walking as children of the light; for if they watch for occaſion, and will falſly accuſe without a cauſe, what would they doe if they had a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:162306:7"/>cauſe; ſeeing they waite for a opportunity, how does it behoove Gods people to walke exactly, as <hi>Goll.</hi> 4.5. Walke wiſely towards thoſe that are without and <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.15. Take heed yee walke circumſpectly what ever others doe, Yee that are children of the light, yee that are the Lords redeemed ones, take heed that yee walke circumſpectly, walke ſo as yee may not give juſt occaſion to the <hi>wicked</hi> to <hi>open their</hi> mouthes againſt religion.</p>
                  <p>But may ſome ſay, though the people of God walke never ſo exactly, yet the <hi>wicked</hi> will charge them with things which they know not.</p>
                  <p>Then firſt conſider, though they doe, yet it will afford the peace of Conſcience when the enemie falſly accuſe thee; truly it will be very comfortable for a poore ſoule to ſay in ſuch a condition? Well, they lay to my charge things that I knew not of.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, conſider it will ſhame your enemies in time when you walke thus exactly; when they are found lyers and ſlanderers, and backbiters, then they will be aſhamed; and againe thirdly, Such exact walking will in time ſtop the mouthes of wicked people whether they will or no; they ſhall in time be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to confeſſe, well, wee made account to have triumphed over ſuch a one, but now wee ſee wee are miſtaken, as 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.15. By well doing yee put to filence the fooliſh people; ſo the people of God by exact walking will in time ſilence the wicked.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond thing that this Doctrine ſhould teach the people of God, is how to carrie themſelves as they ought under falſe reports; but you will ſay, How ſhould a child of God carrie himſelfe under falſe reports, ſo as hee may not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonour God in that condition.</p>
                  <p>I anſwer, Firſt Gods people ſhould beare reproach patiently, Ieſus Chriſt is a very good patterne for the Saints to imitate in this particular, hee did no wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe, neither was there any guile found in his mouth, and yet the text ſaith, <hi>Matth</hi> 8. That he was called a blaſphemer, and a friend of Publicans and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and a Conjurer, and one that caſts out Devils by the help of the Devill; and yet our Saviour Chriſt wee cannot find he anſwered one word againe; the text ſaith, When hee was reviled he reviled not againe, when he ſuffered, hee threatned not but committed it to him that judgeth righteouſly, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.23. <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> delivered him up, <hi>Iudas</hi> betrayed him, <hi>Pilate</hi> condemned him, they ſpit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, crowned him with thornes, bare falſe witneſſe againſt him, put him to death, and yes hee prayes, <hi>Father forgive them they know not what they doe;</hi> So the like wee ſee in <hi>Stephen,</hi> in <hi>Acts</hi> the ſixth, There roſe up falſe witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; and ſaid they heard him ſpeake blaſphemous words againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> and againſt God, and yet for all this they beare falſe witneſſe againſt him, and in juſtly condemned him to death, &amp; ſtoned him with ſtones; He prayed, Lord lay not this ſin to their charge, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.59. Theſe are good patternes for the Saints to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in all their reproaches from the wicked; and there are divers motives may be to the godly as incouragements to this dutie of bearing the reproaches of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed patiently.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Firſt, no falſe reports of men can take away Gods love from them, when the wicked have villified them what they can, ſpake all manner of evill of them to make them odious to others; yet ſtill God loves them, ſtill God ſaith, Hee that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:162306:8"/>toucheth you, toucheth the Apple of his eye, <hi>Zech</hi> 2.8. And ſince thou were precious in my ſight thou wert honourable, and I have loved thee, <hi>Eſay</hi> 43 4. What a comfort is this unto a child of God, when the wicked have done againſt them what they can, though they ſhould ſtudie which way to make them as odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as they can, yet all their plotting againſt them cannot take them out of Gods heart.</item>
                     <item>Secondly, conſider this is a leſſe affliction then God may lay upon them, God may trie them with other manner of ſufferings then theſe; as the Apoſtle ſaith, Yee have not yet reſiſted unto bloud, ſtriving againſt ſinne; God may call his people to lay down their lives for Chriſts ſake, and to forſake all enjoyments under Chriſt, and grace for Chriſts ſake, and the teſtimony of a good Conſcience, and it a godly man cannot beare theſe leſſe afflictions patiently, how ſhall they beare greater afflictions patiently; as <hi>Ier.</hi> 12.5. If thou haſt runne with the foot men, and they have wearied thee, how ſhalt thou match thy ſelfe with horſes; So if thou canſt not beare leſſe afflictions patiently, how wilt thou beare greater afflictions patiently. When they bare falſe witneſſe againſt <hi>Stephen,</hi> hee did not ſay as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a ruſt an will doe if they bee angred, well, I will be revenged of ſuch a one, I will have his bloud for this; no, hee prayes, Lord lay not this ſinne to their charge; Did he beare falſe accuſation, and death it ſelfe ſo patiently, and ſhall not the godly beare the leſſer patiently.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Thirdly, let the godly beare the reproaches of the wicked patiently; becauſe God will one day cleare their innocency, if not in this life yet at the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, at the furtheſt, God will not leave them in the hands of the wicked, nor condemne them when the wicked judge them, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.33. Then the godly ſhall ſtand and the wicked ſhall not be able to ſtand; theſe conſiderations may provoke the people of God to beare reproaches patiently.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, ſuch as would carry themſelves aright under falſe reports muſt walke humbly; It doth not become a gracious ſpirit to be proud though they bee cleare of that which is laid to their charge, leaſt God ſhould give them up to the will of their enemies; God he teaches the humble, guides the humble, dwells with the humble, and in all conditions it becomes Saints to bee humble, and eſpecially when they lie under reproach.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, as humbly, ſo watchfully; It becomes the godly to make the falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations of the wicked their warnings. Oh may the ſoule ſay! I ſee what they would have; I ſee what they would doe if they had juſt cauſe; well, I will bee more watchfull againſt that particular ſin.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, as watchfully ſo thankefully; thankefully will you ſay? What ſhall I bleſſe God that I am falſly accuſed. I anſwer, thou haſt cauſe to be thankefull in a two-fold reſpect, Firſt, that God hath kept thee from that ſinne they lay to thy charge; alas, if God ſhould leave us never ſo little to our ſelves wee doe not know our owne hearts, wee might be as bad as the worſt of all. Secondly, there is cauſe of much thankefulneſſe that God makes the mouthes of the wicked as a warning againſt ſuch, and ſuch a ſinne.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, it is for Inſtruction to all thoſe that are ſo ready to charge the people of God with things which they are cleare of. Let it teach them to take heed how they falſly accuſe any of Gods people; Firſt, conſider what a great ſinne it is, a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:162306:8"/>ſin againſt the 9th. Commandement; Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour. It is a ſinne makes a man reſemble the Devill, the Devill is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the accuſer of the Brethren, this ſinne argues a divelliſh nature, it is ſuch a ſinne as plainely diſcovers there is Murder in the heart.</p>
                  <p>And know thus much, that God heares all thy reviling of his people, all the ſecret malice in the heart, and all thy ſecret ſpeeches againſt any of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; all is knowne to him, thou wouldſt be loth to ſpeak that of thy Neighbour if he were preſent, that thou doſt ſpeake behind his back; but God heard it though thy neighbour did not, and God knowes of all the malice of thy heart, and will one day bring it to light.</p>
                  <p>And as God knowes it, ſo he takes it as done to himſelfe: Ieſus Chriſt is a fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſufferer with his people in all their wrongs, in all their afflictions he is affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 63.9. And hee that touches you toucheth the apple of his eye, <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.8. And if God take the wrongs done to his people as done to himſelf, woe to them that wrong his people.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, as conſider what a great ſinne it is, ſo conſider what ſhame will follow when God cleares the Innocency of his ſervants; What a ſhame it will be for people to ſay, now wee ſee ſuch and ſuch are lyars, ſlanderers, backbiters, and who would truſt them.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, conſider God will never put it up at your hands, your falſe accuſing of his people, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 101.5. Him that privily ſlandereth his Neighbour will I deſtroy. God will be even with them, if they ſeek to deſtroy their Neighbour and God he will deſtroy them.</p>
                  <p>But may ſome ſay; ay, but ſometimes we may ſpeake the truth as well as ſlander them, and what then, ſhall we hold our peace.</p>
                  <p>I anſwer, Firſt it is a great ſinne to accuſe falſly; and as it is a great ſinne to accuſe falſly, ſo in ſome reſpect it is a great ſinne to ſpeake evill of them, though the things be true they ſpeake of.</p>
                  <p>As in caſe the party they ſpeake of be abſent, and yet they will ſpeake evill of a man, this is, though the thing be true, backbiting; and ſee what ſhall become of ſuch, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 140.11. The backbiter ſhall not be eſtabliſhed upon the earth, ſuch a one may thinke to get up by his neighbours ruines but it will not doe; God hath threatned he ſhall not be eſtabliſhed upon the earth.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, in caſe though the thing be true, yet if the parties have been deeply humbled for it, judge themſelves for it, lye upon the rack pleading for mercy, and groaning under the burden of it; and is left in a wilderneſſe of ſorrow, at ſuch a time to revile them, and abuſe them for that which is true, it is a ſinne with a witneſſe, this is to adde affliction to the afflicted, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.26. They doe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute him whom thou haſt ſmitten, and adde ſorrowes to him whom thou haſt wounded; at ſuch a time to ſpeake to the diſgrace of another is a ſinne with a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, in caſe it be a neere friend that they revile, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41.9. My fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar friend whom I truſted, which did eat at my table hath lifted up the heele a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mee, though the thing ſhould bee true, yet when one pretends friendſhip and flatter to a mans face, that they might revile him behind his back without ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion, this diſcovers the envie in the heart, and aggravates the ſinne.</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:162306:9"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> But ſome may ſay, wee may ſpeake any thing, that is true; Shall your preciſe people doe what they liſt, and no body ſhall controule them.</p>
                  <p>I anſwer, in ſome cauſes a man may not ſpeake of the failings of a child of God, and in ſome cauſes they may ſpeake of their failings?</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Firſt, a man hath no ground to ſpeake evill of thoſe things which hee knowes not, in things that wee doe not know are true, and in things that wee doe not know whether ever there were any ſuch thing intended by the parties or no, wee have nothing to doe to condemne them for. I would faine know by what rule, either from the light of nature or grace, a man is to be condemned for things that he knowes not; this is to take Gods place to judge the heart of another, it is God onely that ſearches the heart; and hee hath reſerved it to himſelfe to judge the heart; therefore ſaith Chriſt, Iudge not that yee be not judged, <hi>Matthew</hi> 7.1. And God doth ſeverely puniſh ſuch as take his worke out of his hand; for with what Iudgement ye judge ſaith Chriſt, yee ſhall be judged, and with what meaſure yee meet it ſhall be meaſured to you againe. God bids us looke to our owne hearts, but he forbids us judging the hearts of others; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. Iudge nothing before the time untill the Lord come who will lighten things that are had in darkeneſſe, and if God will doe it, what have any to doe to take his worke out of his hands.</item>
                     <item>Secondly, the godly are not to be evill ſpoken of for meere frailties, and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, which either they take little notice of, or elſe they groane under the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n of, to ſpeake evill of them, or bring a <hi>odium</hi> upon them for ſuch things, it argues that there is malice in the heart.</item>
                     <item>Thirdly, the godly are not to be evill ſpoken of publickly by diſcovering a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, when the revealing of it can no way make for Gods glory or the good of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but rather bring diſhonour to God; it doth argue that that man or woman which diſcovers it, is a ſlanderer, and malicious in heart againſt the other partie; for ſaith the wiſe man, He that goeth about as a ſlanderer diſcovers a ſecret, but he that is of a faithfull heart concealeth a matter, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.13. So they are branded out to be malicious ſlanderers, unfaithfull; It is a ſigne of a wicked heart when people are glad of any thing to ſet upon the ſtage againſt a child of God.</item>
                     <item>Fourthly, the godly are not to be evill ſpoken of behind their back, for as I told you before, God will not put it up at their hands, the backbiter ſhall not bee eſtabliſhed upon the earth.</item>
                     <item>Fifthly, the godly are not to be evill ſpoken of for their goodneſſe, their exact walking with God; but this I have ſpoken of already, and therefore I come to ſhew you in what cauſes the failing of Gods people may be ſpoken of.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Firſt, when private admonition will doe no good, but they remaine obſtinate ſtill, the Lord Ieſus Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Matt.</hi> 18.15. Tell thy brother his fault be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and thee, and if hee heare thee thou haſt wonne thy brother, if heare thee not tell it to two or three; and if he be obſtinate ſtill tell it to the Church, I pray you marke the words, our Saviour doth not bid them goe and tell ſcoffers and jeerers at holineſſe of it, that will indeavour thereby to make God &amp; Religion odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but tell it to the Church that they might come under the Cenſure of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, untill ſuch time as they acknowledge their fault, and give ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the godly concerning the crime; for let a thing be never ſo true of a child of God; they that will ſpeake of it ſo, as to ſet upon the Stage to Gods diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:162306:9"/>the diſgrace of the Goſpell, and the prejudice of Religion; truly it is a ſigne they never yet truly learned what belongs to religion or humanity either.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, in things that are too apparently evill, that is, things that are ſo open and manife<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, that all the Country takes notice of it, then they are to bee reproved openly.</p>
                  <p>Or thirdly, when the ſpeaking of their failings make for Gods glory, and the good of Religion; In theſe cauſes the failings of the Godly may bee ſpoken of, ſo as thoſe that ſpeake of them obſerve theſe cautions; Firſt, that the ground <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> his ſpeaking of his neighbour be nor revenge, and a deſire to diſgrace the other partie; for if theſe be the grounds, though the thing they ſpeake be true, yet their end is evill, and God will find it out and puniſh it, I pray ſee <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.17. Be not thou glad when thy Enemy fals, let not thy heart joy when hee ſtumbles; leaſt the Lord ſee it and be wrath, and turne his wrath from him to thee, if God will bring that plague upon thee that ſhould have come upon thy Enemie, if thou haddeſt not joyed at his downefall; What doeſt thou thinke God will bring upon ſuch, as joy at the downefall of ſuch as are no Enemies.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, It muſt be ſpoken at a fit and convenient time, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.11. A foole poures out all his mind at once, but a prudent man keepeth it untill after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, that is, untill a convenient time, untill his ſpeech may bee ſeaſonable; Words in ſeaſon are as Apples of Gold in pictures of ſilver; and truly, ſuch in the text, are branded with folly as not ſeaſonable in their talke of the failings of the Godly; but every bodie with them is alike, and all times alike for to ſpeake of the failings of the godly; A foole poures out all his mind at once.</p>
                  <p>A fourth <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> is for exhortation; Firſt to thoſe that falſly accuſe the people of God, my exhortation to you is to repent of this your wickedneſſe in time, leaſt you repent too late, Conſider what great bills of inditement, the great God of Heaven and Earth will bring againſt you at the great day, when every ſecret Plot ſhall be diſcovered, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12. <hi>verſe</hi> the laſt, God will bring every worke to Iudgement with every ſecret thing, whether it be good or evill, how will you be able to ſtand then when the Lord ſhall judge between thee and thy neighbour? for this Iudge he will judge according to knowledge, and righteouſly. Magiſtrates may bee ſo corrupt as they may juſtifie the wicked and condemne the Iuſt; and take part with the wicked againſt the people of God; but God will bee a upright Iudge, he will judge according to righteouſneſſe between man and man, yea, he that inhibits Kings to wrong his people, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.15. Hee then will Iudge between Magiſtrates and his people.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, be exhorted to repent of it, ſo to forſake it, and becauſe it is ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching a ſinne, as that when a man or woman is once accuſtomed to it, it is a hard matter to refraine it, I ſhall propound to you the meanes you are to uſe, as ever you would avoid this ſinne of ſlandering your Neighbour.</p>
                  <p>The firſt badge of God to ſhew thee the vileneſſe of thy heart in this particular ſinne; It is ſuch a ſinne as makes a man like the Devill; a ſinne that brands a man or woman to be wicked, a ſinne not onely againſt the Morall Law, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law of nature; Such ſhew the nature of Devills, and wilde beaſts, rather them the nature of men, that will falſly accuſe their Neighbour and ſecke the bloud of their neighbour; and yet it is a ſtrange thing to ſee how common this
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:162306:10"/>ſinne is in our dayes, people doe not account it as a ſinne; and therefore there is great need to beg of God to convince thee of the vildneſſe of it.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, deale by your neighbour as you would be glad hee ſhould deale by you, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.12. Conſider thus with thy ſelfe, would I be glad my neighbour ſhould have dealt by mee as I have dealt by him? would I have been glad that he upon no better grounds then I have accuſed him of a crime, hee ſhould have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed me of the ſame crime.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, another meanes to avoid this ſinne, is to avoid idleneſſe; for Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is the roote of this and many other groſſe ſinnes; The idle perſon is at lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to attend the Devils buſineſſe; and hence it comes to paſſe there is ſo much running from houſe to houſe with tales and falſe reports as there is; becauſe there are ſo many idle perſons that are at leaſure to attend upon the Devils buſineſſe. And truly I thinke there is ſmall reaſon, why any ſhould credit what the Idle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſpeakes, when the Apoſtle exhorts the Saints, 2 <hi>Theſſal.</hi> 3.6. To withdraw themſelves from them, and in the 10th. <hi>verſe</hi> flatly commands, That if there be any will not worke that they ſhould not eat; and <hi>verſe</hi> 11th. For wee heare there are ſome worke not at all but are buſie bodies, buſie in medling with other folks matters, as 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.13: They being Idle learne to goe from houſe to houſe, yea, they are not onely idle but pratlers, buſie bodies; Theſe are the fruits of idleneſſe running about with tales and lies, and flanders, and therefore the way to avoid it is to avoid idleneſſe.</p>
                  <p>The fourth and laſt meanes is, if thou wouldeſt not falſiſie or unjuſtly any way accuſe thy Neighbour, then ſearch thy owne heart firſt, and ſee what is there; and ſo I come to the uſe of Exhortation in generall, as it concernes both the godly and wicked, be all hence exhorted to take heed how you receive falſe reports of the godly; For we muſt know, it is as great ſinne to receive falſe reports as to deviſe them, and tell them forth, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.1. Thou ſhalt not receive a falſe tale nor put thy hand with the wicked to be a falſe witneſſe. God have forbidden the receiving of a falſe tale, as well as the telling of it; wee uſe to ſay of theeves that the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is as bad as the thiefe; ſo the talebearer is as bad as the tale teller, nay worſe, for a man may be a thiefe without a receiver, but there can be no talebearer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a receiver; the hearing of falſe tales as well as the telling of them is abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto the Lord, and it is a ſigne that ſuch men and women are liers and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers themſelves that receive falſe tales, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.4. The wicked heed falſe lips, and the lyar hearkens to falſe lips, I pray marke who they be are ſo readie to receive falſe tales, the wicked, the liar; and on the contrary it is a marke of a child of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.3. He that ſlandereth not with his tongue, nor does evill to his neighbour nor receives a falſe report againſt his neighbour, hee that does ſo and ſo ſhall be a Citizen of Sion; and one thing is not to ſlander or receive a ſlander; and on the contrary they that tell falſe tales, and they that delight in hearing them ſhall be excluded this Citie of <hi>Syon, Revel.</hi> 22.15. Without ſhall be doggs, inchanters, whoremongers, murderers, Idolaters, and whoſoever loveth and maketh lies, I pray marke, not onely thoſe that make them, or thoſe that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe them, but thoſe that love to heare them told forth.</p>
                  <p>Truly I hope I ſhall need no other argument to Gods people but theſe two to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void talebearers, the firſt is, conſider ſuch people are very deſtructive to a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:162306:10"/>a Towne, or a perſon to a Kingdome, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 22.9. You finde it one of the great ſinnes ſet downe in the Catalogue, for which God would take venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance upon them. In the one, they, ſaith the Lord that carrie tales to ſhed bloud, and as to a Kingdome ſo to a Towne, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.20. Where there is no talebearer ſtrife ceaſeth; It implies thus much, that where there is talebearers there is ſtrife, ſtrife between man and man, and many times a whole Towne at variance, and as to a Towne, ſo to a perſon, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.16. Thou ſhalt not goe about with tales among thy people, nor ſtand againſt the bloud of thy neighbour; ſo that in that it ſeckes the bloud of another, it is deſtructive to a perſon.</p>
                  <p>My ſecond motive is, Conſider what a ſad fight it would be to ſee a child of God in a Devils habit; but you will ſay, how ſhall wee avoid hearing of tales; I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>Solomon</hi> tells you how, <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.23. As the North wind driveth away raine, ſo doth the angrie countenance the ſlanderous tongue; if you ſharpely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them and not hearken to them; they will ſoone bee weary of the trade, it they can no longer utter their ware, and the reaſon why there is ſo many of that trade, is, becauſe they have ſo many merchants to put off their ware to.</p>
                  <p>I might here, it time did permit ſhew how this concernes Magiſtrates, if Gods people may be falſly accuſed, it concernes them to take heed how they joyne with the wicked againſt the people of God; Magiſtrates are to juſtifie the righteous and condemne the wicked, <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.1. They ought to imitate God in Iudgement, to judge according to righteouſneſſe, and not for favour and affection; but I leave this and conclude with this word of conſolation to all thoſe that are falſly accuſed, <hi>Iames</hi> 5.9. Behold the Iudge ſtandeth at the doore; Take my brethren the Prophets for a example of ſuffering adverſitie, and of long patience which have ſpoken in the name of the Lord, and <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 11th. Bleſſed ſhall yee be when men revile you and perſecute you, and ſay all manner of evill againſt you for my ſake falſly, rejoyce and be glad, for great is your reward in Heaven; for ſo perſecuted they the Prophets which were before you.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:162306:11"/>
                  <p>THE Skillfull Teacher.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IN</hi> A SERMON PRECAED At CHILISFORD in <hi>Suffolk, July</hi> the 16. <hi>Anno</hi> 1648.</p>
                  <p>BY ZEPH. SMITH.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>2 TIMOTHY 2.15.</hi>
                     </bibl> Study to ſhew thy ſelfe approved of God, a worke-man that needeth not to be aſhamed, dividing the word of truth aright.</q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>LUKE 22.32.</hi>
                     </bibl> When thou art Converted, ſtrgenthen thy Brethren.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by THO: FORCET for <hi>John Rothwell,</hi> living in <hi>Pauls-Church-yard,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the ſigne of the Sun and the Fountaine, in the yeare, 1648.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:162306:11"/>
                  <head>THE Skilfull Teacher.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>PSAL. 51.13.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>Then ſhall I teach thy wayes unto the wicked.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Pſalme is <hi>Davids</hi> penitentiall Pſalme, in which after <hi>Nathan</hi> came to him and reproved him for his ſinne of murther and adultery; he confeſſes his ſinne and petitions to God for mercy for himſelfe and the Church; for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to <hi>verſe</hi> 18. And for the Church to the end of the Pſalme; In the firſt part of the Pſalme wee have his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his ſinne, and his Petition for pardon to the 8th. <hi>verſe;</hi> In which wee may take notice of the Prophets diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe; <hi>viz.</hi> A wounded ſpirit for ſinne. Secondly, that he ſeeke for as a ſpeciall remedie to cure this diſeaſe, Is ſinne pardoning mercy, loving kindneſſe, and multitude of mercies; The Prophet knew his ſinne was great and acknowledged it to be ſo, and therefore hee calls for much ſin-pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning mercy, intreating the Lord to waſh him throughly from all his ſinnes, and eſpecially from theſe foule ſinnes of murther and adulterie.</p>
                  <p>God doth not onely wound the Spirits of his people for ſinne at their firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion; but alſo if afterward they fall into ſinne as did <hi>David,</hi> he brings them back againe through a wilderneſſe of ſorrow to comfort. <hi>Peter</hi> denied his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter after Converſion; God brings him to his comfort through the rivers of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter teares, hee wept bitterly; and doe wee not ſee the like in <hi>David;</hi> I doe not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:162306:12"/>ſay their ſinnes after Converſion ſeperates them from the Love of God, for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can ſeparate true belcevers from the love of God, <hi>Rom</hi> 8.38. But though their ſinnes cannot ſeperate them from Gods love, yet they may deprive them of the comfortable injoyment of the light of Gods countenance, and God ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily brings them through a wilderneſſe of ſorrow to the ſight of it againe; it coſt them many a prayer and teare, many a ſigh out of bitterneſſe of Spirit. As <hi>David,</hi> who pleads for pardon of ſinne, and earneſtly deſires God would aſſure him of his pardon of his ſinne before he had the comfort of it; for though <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> ſaid to him when hee tried out I have ſinned; thy ſinne as pur away from thee, thou ſhalt not die; yet the Prophet cried out of the bitterneſſe of his ſoule, and went up and downe with a heavie heart a long time before hee had the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of it; as appeares by his prayer, <hi>verſe</hi> the 8th. Make mee to heare of joy and gladneſſe that the bones which thou haſt broken may rejoyce; <hi>Davids</hi> ſinfull carnall joy proved the breaking of his bones, at laſt though ſinne be ſweet at the committing, yet the laſh that followes will be as bitter as gall and wormewood; Well might the Prophet have ſaid, Oh! accurſed be that pleaſure that ends in ſuch paine, that procures ſuch ſorrow, and hinders me of ſuch joy, as now a drop of it would be better to mee then a whole World; though ſin hath broke my bones, yet a drop of that Ioy would cauſe them to rejoyce —and in the 10th. <hi>verſe,</hi> The Prophet prayes for ſanctifying grace, hee doth not onely pray for pardoning grace but purging grace; Create in mee a cleane heart, a ſincere Convert will not onely deſire to be juſtified but to be ſanctified; to be holy as well as happy, to have the power of godlineſſe as well as the forme, As if the Prophet ſhould have ſaid, Lord, I doe not onely deſire to have my ſinnes pardoned but my heart purged; my heart is filthy and polluted; Oh create in mee a cleane heart; — In the 11th <hi>verſe,</hi> He petitions for deliverance from that Iudgement that fell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Saul; viz.</hi> Rejection, Caſt me not away from thy preſence; as if hee ſhould have ſaid, Lord, my predeceſſour <hi>Saul;</hi> hee ſinned againſt thee and thou didſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject him for a King; and if thou ſhouldſt reject mee, and ſay; becauſe that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> hath done this I will reject him, he ſhall be King no longer; hee ſhall rule the people no longer, thou wort juſt and righteous, but oh-caſt mee not away from thy preſence, — then in the 12th. <hi>verſe,</hi> He prayes for that ancient com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort he once injoyed; Reſtore to mee the joy of thy Salvation, the word Reſtore to mee doth implie, that the Prophet once had it and now had loſt it; whence we may obſerve, that though ſinne doe not deprive the godly of Heaven, yet it will deprive them of their joy for a time; Sinne will bring a child of light to walke in darkneſſe and to ſee no light of comfort, as the ſoule ſhall bee conſtrained to ſay, What have I to doe any more with Idols, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 14.9. If theſe ſorrowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and afflictions and horrours be the effects of ſinnefull joy, What have I to doe with ſinne, I will returne to my firſt husband, for at that time was I better then now; Oh reſtore to mee the joy of thy ſalvation, and eſtabliſh mee with thy free Spirit.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, hence wee may obſerve, that when a ſoule is ſenſible of the abſence of the light of Gods countenance, it is reſtleſſe untill God ſpeake peace; how reſtleſſe was the Spouſe in ſeeking after Chriſt, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3. How reſtleſſe was the man, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88. How reſtleſſe was <hi>David</hi> in the abſence of the light of Gods
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:162306:12"/>Countenance, hee waſhes his couch with his teares, his moyſture was turned into the drought of Summer, he roared all the day, he bewailes his ſinne, hee cries out; Make mee to heare of joy and gladneſſe, reſtore to mee the joy of thy Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; Hee ſets a high price upon it and accounts it better then life, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.3. Hee promiſes that if ever God will ſpeake peace to him hee will walke more exactly for the future, as in the text, <hi>Then will I teach tranſgreſſours thy wayes;</hi> as much as if hee ſhould have ſaid, Lord, if ever thou wilt ſpeake peace to my ſoule, if ever thou wilt bring mee out of theſe ſtraites my ſinnes have brought mee into, Lord if ever thou wilt pardon my ſinne and receive mee into favour, then I ſhall be able to teach and inſtruct others experimentally, I ſhall bee a faire warning to others to avoyd the like ſinnes I have committed; and I ſhould be able to comfort others in the like diſtreſſe I am in.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Then ſhall I teach,</hi> The Scripture makes mention of the teaching of God, the teaching of Chriſt, and the teachings of the Spirit, both ordinary and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary; ſo of the teachings of men, ſuch as are good or bad, ſuch as teach the word of the Lord faithfully, and ſuch as teach fantaſies of their owne braine and lyes, and deluſions; Amongſt men there are two ſorts of Teachers, ſuch as are publich Teachers; and Private, that is, ſuch as inſtruct their Families and Neighbours, as occaſion is offered in the wayes of God, though not in a publique Miniſteriall way, as they, that are ſet apart for the publique Miniſterie. I finde not in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that <hi>David</hi> tooke upon him the Office of the Prieſt or Levites, and taught publickely as thoſe ſet apart for the worke; Then the Queſtion is, what hee meanes by teaching here, when he ſaith, Then will I teach. I anſwer, The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David</hi> taught in his Family, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.20. He returned from dancing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Arke to bleſſe his houſe, that was, to pray with them and inſtruct them; Secondly, as a King, occaſionally by inſtructing his Subjects as occaſion was offered, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.9. I have declared thy righteouſneſſe in the great Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and thirdly, He taught as a Prophet, infallibly inſpired and moved by the holy Ghoſt to pen part of the holy Scripture. The duty of teaching lies upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Maſter of a Family to pray with them, and Catechiſe them, and inſtruct them in Gods wayes, according to that abilitie God hath given them; though not the like duty as a King, as <hi>David</hi> did, or as one infallibly inſpired now as <hi>David</hi> was then; Neither doth this text prove as ſome groſſely imagine, that all believers may teach in a publique Miniſteriall way; for if all be Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Who ſhall be taught? But the ſenſe of the text runnes thus; then, if God will reſtore to me the joy of his Salvation, and bring mee out of theſe ſtraites, then I ſhall according to my place experimentally ſhew to others how bitter ſinne is, and how good God is in pardoning ſinners, according to the expreſſion of the Prophet, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66. Come all yee that feare the Lord, and I will tell you what he hath done for my ſoule.</p>
                  <p>In the text wee have <hi>Davids</hi> promiſe, and <hi>Davids</hi> Prophocie; his Promiſe, then will I teach; his Propheſie, and ſinners ſhall bee converted unto thee; or here is the duty hee bindes himſelfe to performe, and the ſucceſſe hee promiſes to himſelfe, that which wee are to inſiſt upon, is the duty which the Prophet binds himſelfe to performe, in which conſider firſt that it was, — <hi>Teach.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, the Doctrine, he will teach — <hi>the wayes,</hi> that is, Gods wayes.</p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:162306:13"/>
                  <p>Thirdly, the perſons he will teach, — the wicked.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, the time when hee will teach, — then will I teach; that is, when God ſpeakes peace to him, and reſtores to him the joy of his Salvation, then hee will teach others; from whence in the firſt place wee learne this point of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, That thoſe perſons whoſe ſpirits God have wounded for ſinne, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward reſtored to comfort are beſt able to teach and inſtruct others: Then will I teach; as it he had ſaid, then ſhall I bee able to teach from my owne experience. It is thoſe that are taught themſelves are beſt able to teach others; Thou that teacheſt another ſaith the Apoſtle, teacheſt thou not thy ſelfe? A man that is not might himſelfe, nor able to teach himſelfe is not fit to teach others: When thou art converted ſaith Chriſt to <hi>Peter,</hi> ſtrengthen thy Brethren, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.32. As if he ſhould have ſaid, <hi>Peter,</hi> when thou haſt experience of Gods goodneſſe thy ſelfe, thou wilt be able to teach others; then ſtrengthen thy weake Brethren. Thoſe that God hath brought under the terrours of Conſcience, they knowing the terrour of the Lord will from their owne experience acquaint others with it, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. And they having comfort from God are beſt able to comfort others; Who comforteth us ſaith the Apoſtle in all our tribulations, that we might be able to comfort others, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4. As much as if hee ſhould have ſaid, untill a man have experience of Gods goodneſſe himſelfe, hee will not be able to comfort an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; and the experience of Gods goodneſſe makes a man able from experience to comfort others; therefore God comforts his in all their tribulations that they might be able to comfort others.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Reaſon of the point is, becauſe ſuch can teach others experimentally; for the Lord having opened their owne eyes, and ſhewed them the horrible filthineſſe of ſinne; what Monſters they are, how by nature they are children of wrath, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3. That they have defaced the Image of God, and have the Image of Satan; that they lie in their bloud and filthineſſe, <hi>Ezechiell</hi> 16.8. And ſhewed them the fountaine of Chriſt's bloud, <hi>Zechariah</hi> 13.1. In that day there ſhall bee a fountaine opened to the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> and the Inhabitants of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to waſh in, for ſinne and for uncleanneſſe; and made them tunne to this fountaine with <hi>David,</hi> Purge me, waſh mee; they can experimentally declare this to others.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, they know by experience what folly and madneſſe it is to runne on in the wayes of ſinne, and they can informe others of it; <hi>Paul</hi> hee had found the ſervice of ſinne a fruitleſſe ſervice himſelfe, and hee appeales to others, whether they had not found it ſo alſo, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.21. What fruit found yee in thoſe things whereof yee are now aſhamed; Thoſe that know the folly, and madneſſe, and fruitleſſeneſſe in the ſervice of ſinne, they can experimentally informe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, they have felt the burden of ſinne themſelves, and they can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to others what a preſſing burden ſinne is; ſinne is ſuch a burden as will ſinke the ſoule if it bee not disburdened; When the weight of ſinne oppreſſed <hi>Davids</hi> Conſcience, hee cryed out, My iniquities are gone over my head, they are a burden too heavie for mee to beare, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.4. When the Lord intends good to the foule, hee layes the burden of ſinne upon the Conſcience, that it might runne to Chriſt who onely can eaſe it; Who alſo invites ſuch to come to him,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:162306:13"/>
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 11.28. Come unto mee all yee that labour and are heavie laden, and I will eaſe you. Yee that labour under the burden of ſinne, and crie helpe, I ſinke, I periſh, I periſh, them Chriſt eaſes, and then they can tell their friends and Neighbours experimentally ſinne will preſſe the ſinner, if ever God intend good to the ſoule here; for though ſome are preſſed with the burden of it more then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, yet all feele the burden of it in ſome meaſure; and if they feel not the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing burden of ſinne here for their good, it will preſſe them to hell for ever with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope of recovery; and therefore, woe to thoſe men and women that Ieſus Chriſt eaſes not of this burden.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, they have been made ſenſible of their ſpirituall bondage, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude to ſinne and Satan; A man that hath been in Captivity, and made a ſlave to his Enemies, can tell by experience whet bondage and captivity is. We are all by nature bond-ſlaves to ſinne and Satan; we were borne ſlaves and have lived ſlaves, a worſe ſlavery then the Turkes or any other Nations ſlavery; but natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall people are not ſenſible of it; It is thoſe that have been made ſenſible of it that can beſt informe others about it.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, they have taſted the bitterneſſe of ſinne, and they can declare to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers what bitters fruits ſinne brings forth; though ſinne be in the mouth as ſweet as honey, yet in the belly it will be bitter; afterwards it brings bitterneſſe; <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> found it true by experience, when hee cryed out, my ſinne is ever before mee; Ever when I lie downe and when I riſe up, where ever I am, or what ever I doe, my ſinne is ever before me, my Conſcience alwayes accuſes mee. <hi>Iob</hi> found ſinne bitter alſo, <hi>Iob</hi> 13.26. Thou writeſt bitter things againſt mee, and cauſeſt mee to poſſeſſe the ſinnes of my youth; God brought his ſinne to remembrance, and his Conſcience accuſes him, this was bitter; thou writeſt bitter things againſt mee; Sinne will end in bitterneſſe; Behold! it is an evill thing and bitter to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Lord, <hi>Ier.</hi> 2.19. It will make the ſinner to mourne in bitterneſſe, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12 10. They ſhall mourne for him and be in bitterneſſe, they may pray in bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe, heare the word in bitterneſſe, not finde one word of comfort in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances; they may thinke upon God in bitterneſſe; ſaith <hi>David,</hi> I thought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God and was troubled, I prayed and my ſpirit was full of anguiſh, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.3. Though hee thought upon God and prayed to him, who is the ſoules life, comfort, joy, all in all, yet he was troubled; So the poore ſinner may pray and be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, heare and bee troubled, read and be troubled, looke up to Heaven and bee troubled, thinke upon God and be troubled; Like a Mariner in a ſtorme, when hope failes of ſafetie he cries out, What ſhall I doe? I ſinke, I periſh. So ſayes the ſoule in the bitterneſſe of ſpirit, I ſinke and periſh, I am damned, my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience that is a rolle, wherein is written Lamentations, and mourning, and woe; Now I ſee by experience, it is an evill thing and bitter to forſake the Lord. Now that ſoule that hath taſted the bitterneſſe of ſinne can experimentally teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers how bitter ſinne is; A man that hath indured impriſonment, or that hath indured ſickneſſe can beſt tell what it is; A man that hath had the Pox or the Plague, and recovered it, can experimentally tell what it is. So they that have ſeen the plague of a hard heart, the plague-ſore of ſinne, they can beſt declare to others the bitterneſſe of it.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. They have taſted of Gods goodneſſe alſo, and they can experimentally ſhew
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:162306:14"/>to others how gracious the Lord is, how gracious the Lord hath been to them in reſtoring peace to them; as they have been acquainted with the bitterneſſe of ſinne; So with the Lords comming into the ſoule with comfort; they can expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimentally tell others God doth not alway hide his face; though for a time the ſoule may looke up to the Lord that hides his face, <hi>Eſa</hi> 8.17. Yet he will not hide his face alwayes, though the Spouſe mourne a long time after him whom her ſoule loveth, yet at the length ſhe finds him. <hi>Cant.</hi> 3. For a moment, in my anger ſaith the Lord, I hid my face, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 54.8. But with everlaſting kindneſſe will I have compaſſion on thee; and they can declare to others how the Lord returned in mercy to them, when they were ready to ſinke, when hope failed, and they were ready to deſpaire, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the Prophet ſaith in the fatherleſſe finde mercy, <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſea</hi> 14.4. I was ſaith the ſoule as on fatherleſſe, and motherleſſe, and friendleſſe, and harbourleſſe, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended my ſelfe ſinking downe to hell without hope or help; I ſee I had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, nor had done nothing that would commend mee to God, and yet in my diſpairing condition, when I ſaid I am caſt off, the Lord of his free grace found mee a loſt ſheep; A prodigall child that fed upon husks untill my ſoule was ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; and the Lord drew me to Chriſt, and commanded his loving kindneſſe to take hold upon me, hee overcame mee and made ſick of love to leſus Chriſt. And now I ſee that Chriſt is all in all; the ſight of God as a reconciled Father in Ieſus Chriſt, that is, ſoule-ſatisfying comfort; one ſmile from the Father in Ieſus Chriſt countervailes all the bitterneſſe I have undergone; Now I thinke I ſhould be able to comfort others in the like diſtreſſe, and this is the firſt reaſon; they can teach others experimentally.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond Reaſon is, becauſe they are moſt skilfull to miniſter a word in ſeaſon to a drooping ſoule; If a man inquire the way to a place, hee that hath been at that place is more skilfull to direct him then one that either knowes it by heare-ſay, or by the Map; They can ſpeake as they have heard or read, but hee that hath been there he ſpeaks according to knowledge, hee ſpeaks that he hath ſeen; A man may teach many profitable truths to others, and yet never found the power of them himſelfe. I beat downe my body ſaith the Apoſtle, and bring it into ſubjection, leaſt, while I preach to others I my ſelfe ſhould be a caſtaway. Is it poſſible for a man to teach others and yet not bee taught himſelfe; A man may preach of the Doctrine of Faith, and Repentance, and Obedience to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; As the man that directs the other the way by the Map; but hee that hath found Faith and Repentance, and walks with God, hee can teach others experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally. They that walke in the way to Heaven are more skilfull to direct an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other the way, then they that direct them by heare-ſay; The Saints knowes what enemies and tocks and dangers are in the way to heaven, and they can acquaint others with them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Uſe</hi> of the point is to informe us, that it is very neceſſary, that they that teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers be taught themſelves. Thou that teacheſt another ſaith the Apoſtle, teacheſt thou not thy ſelfe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.21. It is that man that hath groaned under the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of his owne luſts and corruptions, and overcomes them, that is beſt able to teach another how to overcome his luſts and corruptions; Truly a man is not fit to teach as a Miniſter untill hee be taught himſelfe to know God, and Chriſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly; nor fit to adviſe as a Chriſtian untill hee bee taught in the Schoole of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:162306:14"/>Chriſt; Were a man taught all the Arts and Sciences under Heaven, were hee able to ſpeake with ſuch acuteneſſe and Elequence as ſhould cauſe admiration in the hearers; yet all this is nothing to the ſaving knowledge of Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Paul</hi> had as good bringing up as another, yet hee counted all as droſſe and dung in compariſon of the excellent knowledge of Chriſt; Arts and Sciences, and parts are neceſſary, but the ſaving knowledge of Ieſus Chriſt is the <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum neceſſarium</hi> for a Teacher; therefore it is very neceſſarie that they that teach others bee taught ſavingly the knowledge of Chriſt, as well as literally your knowledge of the Letter.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, it informes us, that if thoſe that are converted themſelves be fitteſt Inſtruments to convert others: then how unfit are ſuch for the worke of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry as are enemies to Converſion: Such as daube people with untempered morter, and teach lies for truth, and crie peace, peace, when there is no peace; Such as diſcourage people rather then incourage them in the wayes of God, and alſo as bad in their let examples of drunkenneſſe, Sabbath prophanation, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, Idleneſſe, ſwearing, and theſe yet are the men cryed up, and highly eſteemed in the world; aye, but if God account them unfit Miniſters, it mattert not what account the world hath of them; they muſt needs bee very unfit to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect poore ſoules the way to Heaven that are themſelves walking in the way to Hell; and enemies to thoſe that walke to Heaven; Such as refuſe to walke in the wayes of God themſelves, and hinder as many as they can from walking in them, ſurely theſe are unfit to teach others his wayes.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, if thoſe whoſe ſpirits God wounds for ſinne, and after reſtores to comfort be beſt able to teach others, it informes us that God does bring thoſe ſoules hee intends good o through a wilderneſſe of terrour to comfort, I will allure her and bring her into the wilderneſſe, and ſpeake friendly to her, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.14. The Spouſe comes out of the wilderneſſe leaning upon her wel beloved, <hi>Can:</hi> 8.5. Therefore in the next place it is for a uſe of direction to ſuch as would ſeeke unto others in their ſtraites; to make choyce of ſuch Teachers as are beſt able to adviſe them as neere as they can, ſuch as can adviſe them experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally. The ſick man will goe to ſuch a Phyſitian as hee is perſwaded is skilfull, and experienced; Wee ſhould be as carefull for our ſoules, to make choice of ſuch ſpirituall Phyſitians as are skilfull experienced men; And it renders a man or woman ſuſpicious, when in their troubles they goe to ſuch as will daube them up, and flatter them in their ſinne, ſuch as will prophecie peace when there is no peace; and cannot indure them that deale faithfully with them. Firſt, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, an unskilfull unexperienced Phyſitian may inſtead of recovering the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient make the diſeaſe more dangerous, if this bee thy ſoules condition it is very ſad.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, conſider when the Patients life or death depends upon the Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans skill, if the Phyſitian want skill the patient dies: When thy ſoule is ſic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thou ſtandeſt upon the brinke of eternitie, if thou goeſt to unskilfull Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thou mayſt periſh for ever. Ieſus Chriſt is the ſoules beſt Phyſition, the way to be healed is to goe to him; and to aske Counſell of ſuch Phyſitians as have been healed by him, and have learned their skill of him.</p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:162306:15"/>
                  <p>Secondly, as I would adviſe ſuch as are in diſtreſſe to ſeeke to a skilfull Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſo alſo as neere as they can to one that is faithfull; If a Phyſitian have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much skill, if hee be unfaithfull, hee may doe hurt as well as good with his skill; then above all make ſure of a faithfull Phyſitian for the ſoule, one that will faithfully applie the word to thy ſoule ſutable to thy condition, whether it makes for thee or againſt thee; one that will bee faithfull in keeping ſecrets, It becomes not a faithfull Miniſter to diſcloſe thoſe ſecrets that wounded ſpirits reiate to them, but rather to pitie them, and pray for them, and adviſe them; this is the duty of a Phyſitian that is faithfull, and ſuch Phyſitians ſick ſoules ſhould ſeek unto for advice. I Now come to the ſecond Doctrine: Then ſhall I teach. Whence wee learne that when a man is once converted himſelfe, hee will endeavour the converſion of others; If hee bee a Miniſter, when hee is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted himſelfe, what paines will he take to convert others; hee will pray and ſtudy, and ſweat, preaching the Word in ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſon and out of leaſon, hee will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider Chriſt have died to bring home ſoules to God; and ſhall not I whom hee hath ſet as a watchman over ſoules, ſtudie, and ſweat and travell in birth, till Chriſt bee formed in them, yea, and beſeech them in Chriſt's ſtead to bee recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled unto God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20.</p>
                  <p>What meane the faithfull Miniſters preaching the word in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, their reproving, rebuking, exhorting; not as carnall people ſay the Miniſter beare us ill will, and therefore hee reproves us and threatens us with damnation and Iudgement; no, but becauſe they would faine bring home ſoules to God; they are converted themſelves, and they deſire the Converſion of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; ſo private Chriſtians, when God hath once converted them, they will take paines to convert others. When Chriſt told the woman in <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. I hat he was the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> ſhee left her waterpot and water to goe call others to ſee Chriſt; When God hath converted the husband, hee will indeavour the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of his wife, hee will pray for her and inſtruct her in the wayes of God, So when God hath converted the wife, ſhee will endeavour the Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her husband. So converted Parents will pray for their Children, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them, and indeavour their Converſion, and wiſh, oh! that the Lord would grant that my ſonne or daughter might live in his fight; and they will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the Converſion of their friends and Neighbours, they will pray for them, and adviſe and counſell them, and mourne over them, and intice them to that which is good.</p>
                  <p>The Reaſon is, becauſe ſaving grace will not be Idle, it will act; goodneſſe is of a ſpreading nature; <hi>Paul,</hi> when hee was converted himſelfe, ſee what paines he takes to convert others; hee will with-hold nothing that is profitable for the good of ſoules. When <hi>Agrippa</hi> ſaid to him, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.29. Almoſt thou perſwadeſt mee to be a Chriſtian, hee ſaid, I would to God that not onely thou, but all that heare me this day were not almoſt but altogether ſuch as I am, except bonds; his deſire was, that all that heard him might be truly converted, yea, bee did ſo earneſtly deſire the Converſion and Salvation of his Brethren, and Countrymen, that <hi>Romans</hi> 9.2. Hee could have wiſtred himſelfe accurſed from Chriſt, that they might have been ſaved. So <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> hee was converted and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:162306:15"/>God conſtantly himſelfe, and hee reſolves with his Family to ſerve the Lord: So <hi>Abraham</hi> will teach his Children after him the way of the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18, 19. I know <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaith the Lord, that hee will teach his children, and his houſhold after him to keepe the way of the Lord. What is the Reaſon goodneſſe is of a ſpreading nature? True grace cannot in this ſenſe bee hid; Though all be not Gold that gliſters, yet true Gold will gliſter Yee are faith Chriſt, the light of the World. A Citie ſet on a hill cannot be hid; True grace where it is will diſcover it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Is it ſo that ſuch as are converted themſelves will indeavour the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of others; then what an evident ſigne is it, ſuch are not converted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as indeavour not the Converſion of others, but rather intiſe them to ſinne; to Swearing, Drunkenneſſe, Sabbath prophanation, lying, ſlandering; Yea, What ſhall wee thinke of ſuch as are Enemies to Converſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſuch as ſcoffe and ſteere at Converted people; Surely ſuch are farre from ſaving Converſion. To enter into particulars, Doe we ſee Majeſtrates inſtead of puniſhing ſinne, and ſtanding up for ſinne; neglect to reforme themſelves, and neglect to reforme in their Families; but ſuffer their children and ſervants to lie oft, and ſlander and abuſe the people of God; yea, it may bee to ſcoffe at them behinde the doore; Doe we ſee them inſtead of ſetting good examples fet bad examples; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of ſtanding up for the furtherance or the Goſpell hinder it what they can, by oppoſing godly Miniſters; and pleading for ignorant ſottiſh ſcandalous Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, ſwearers, pot companions, drawers on of others to ſinne with greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; Whatſoever their pretext is, if according to the words of our Saviour Chriſt, we may judge of the tree by the fruit, it is evident ſuch Magiſtrates are not ſincere Converts.</p>
                  <p>So ſuch Miniſters as daube people with untempered morter, flatter them in their ſinnes, ſad the hearts of the righteous, and ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked; teach not the people the difference betwixt the holy and prophane, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 44.23. Perſecute the faithfull Maniſters of the word; and inſtead of exhorting people to pray in their Families, and to read the word, ſcoffe and deride at them that doe; ſure ſuch Miniſters are not ſincere Converts, for if they were converted themſelves they would endeavour the Converſion of others. — So ſuch private perſons as neglect prayer in their Family, reading of the word, inſtructing the ſoules committed to their charge in the wayes of God, are content to venture their owne ſoules, their Childrens ſoules, and ſervants ſoules under a ſoule-ſtarving Miniſter. It is evident theſe are not ſincere Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts; for if they were truly converted themſelves, they would ſet up the worſhip of God in their Families, they would deſire the Ordinances of God in the purity; As new borne babes they would deſire the ſincere milke of the word, that they might grow thereby, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. They would inquire where Chriſt feeds his flocks at noone time, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.7. They would crie with <hi>David,</hi> How amiable are thy Tabernacles oh Lord God of Hoſts, my ſoule longeth, yea, and fainteth for the Courts of the Lord, my heart and my fleſh cryeth our for the living God; And I had rather bee a doore keepes in the houſe of God then to dwell in the tents of the wicked, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. They would bee carefull of their owns ſoules, and the ſoules of their Family.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:162306:16"/>2. <hi>Uſe,</hi> If converted perſons will endeavour the Converſion of others, it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes us that there is very few converted now adayes; Where ſhall wee find them that indeavour the Converſion of others. Looke amongſt great men, ſuch as are in eminent places; Doe not the Scripture ſay, Not many high, not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mighty, not many noble are called; And doth not our Saviour ſay, The Myſteries of the Goſpel are hid from the wiſe, and underſtanding in the world, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.25. And is it not written, that builders laid aſide Chriſt the corner ſtone, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.11. How few men in eminent places ſtand up for God. Where ſhall we find converted Magiſtrates, and converted Gentlemen now adayes? If this bee their Character to ſeeke the Converſion of others. So how few Converts ſhall wee find amongſt Miniſters now adayes. Where are they that pray and ſtudy, and preach, and ſweat to convert ſoules? And that mourne for the obſtinacy of the people, when they ſee their Miniſtery convere not ſoules to God, as <hi>Ierem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ah</hi> did. <hi>Ier.</hi> 13.17. It for all this yee will not heare, my ſoule ſhall weep in ſecret for your pride: And my eyes ſhall run downe teares, becauſe the Lords flock is carried away captive; Whether they would heare or no, the Prophet will mourne for their obſtinacie and hardneſſe of heart; So when a faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is diligent to preach the word in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, dividing the word of truth aright, with a deſire to bring home ſoules to God; And yet the word proves a hardning letter; It makes them goe up and downe mourning with the Prophet, I have laboured in vaine, I have ſpent my ſtrength in vaine, the bellowes are burnt, and the lead is conſumed in the fire, and the Founder melteth in vaine; for the wicked are not taken away, reprobate ſilver ſhall men call them; becauſe the Lord hath rejected them; But where ſhall we finde ſuch Miniſters; Now wee may find many, pervert people; Some with their corrupt Doctrine; ſome with their flatteries and prophaneneſſe; but where ſhall wee find ſuch as goe about the worke in good earneſt, to indeavour to convert ſoules to God. Truly, when wee looke abroad amongſt the watchmen of our time, I feare wee ſhall finde but few ſuch. Some few there are I am perſwaded, make it their indeavour to convert ſoules, that ſtudie to approve themſelves to God, workmen that needeth not to bee aſhamed; Theſe are ſo farre I am confident from taking offence at what I ſay now, that they rather groane under their bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and mourne for the lukewarmeneſſe and prophaneneſſe of many of the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of our time; for if this be a Character of a ſincere Convert, to indeavour the Converſion of others. How few of the watchmen of our time are ſincere Converts. So, amongſt the ordinary ſort of people, where ſhall wee find ſincere Converts? As for the moſt part of people, they ſcarce have a forme of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe; but are ſuch as lye in groſſe prophaneneſſe, or ſuch as are but meere groſſe Civilians. And to come to profeſſours, the Scripture ſaith, many of them have a forme of godlineſſe and deny the power: Me thinks my heart hath laine like a ſtone in me; many times when I have tooke notice of ſuch as have been glorious Profeſſours, yea, eminent bright ſtarres to the view of the World: When I have taken notice how little Religion they have had in their Families, how little reading the word, or praying in their Families at any time; Some neglecting morning duties; ſome neglecting morning and evening both; and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:162306:16"/>done no more for their Children and ſervants then they have done for their beaſts, provides for their bodies for the day, and let their ſoules ſinke or ſwimme; It hath often made mee thinke of the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> how he hath cryed out in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12. Help Lord, for there is not a godly man left; A faithfull man who can find ſaith the wiſe man. How few are there ſet up the worſhip of God in their Families? Where ſhall wee find Husbands mourning over their uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Wives, and wives mourning over their unconverted husbands? and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents mourning over their Children, and ſervants that miſcarrie; as <hi>David</hi> did for <hi>Abſolon,</hi> when he cried out, Oh! my ſonne <hi>Abſolon,</hi> my ſonne, my ſon, <hi>Abſolon;</hi> Would God I had died for thee my ſonne, my ſonne; Where there is true Converſion, there will bee an indeavour to convert others: and therefore it is to be feared there is but a few ſincere Converts now a dayes.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Vſe,</hi> is for examination, Let us trie our ſelves, whether or no woe be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted our ſelves; Doe wee indeavour the converſion of others? How does it concerne all ſorts of people to come and weigh themſelves in the ballance of the Sanctuary, and inquire into their conditions; What fruits of Converſion ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares in mee as a Magiſtrate, as a Miniſter, as a Maſter of a Family? How doe I indeavour the Converſion of others? what care have I of my owne ſoule? my Childrens ſoules, and Neighbours ſoules; and how doe I mourne for them that remaine obſtinate? Doe I with <hi>Lot</hi> vex for the abominations of the place where I live; And complaine with <hi>David,</hi> Woe is mee that I am conſtrained to dwell in <hi>Meſech,</hi> and inhabit in the rents of <hi>Kedar;</hi> If thou be a true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert thus it will be with thee; It is very remarkable, the example of the Thiefe upon the Croſſe, hee was converted at the laſt houre, and that very houre, or part of an houre, his grace diſcovered it ſelfe, hee ſought the Converſion of the other thiefe, as you may ſee in <hi>Luke</hi> 23.40. And the truth is, true grace will diſcover it ſelfe. When a ſoule hath once taſted of Gods goodneſſe, and free grace in Ieſus Chriſt, it cannot but deſire that others might taſte it. Oh! that my husband, my wife, my ſonne, my daughter, my Neighbours; oh! that their ſoules might live; Let us examine our ſelves, is it thus with us.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, if wee be converted our ſelves, wee rejoyce as the Converſion of others. The converted Magiſtrate will joy to ſee the Goſpel flouriſh, and the Kingdoms of Heaven ſuffer violence; The converted Miniſter will rejoyce to ſee Chriſt formed in his Auditors, and to ſee them walke in the wayes of the Lord; The wife will rejoyce at the husbands Converſion, and the husband at the wives, and Parents at their Childrens Converſion; there is joy in Heaven for one ſinner that is converted, <hi>Luke</hi> 15. But if wee be ſuch as never regard our owne ſoules, nor the ſoules of others; Such, as inſtead of indeavouring the Converſion of others, pervert them; doe what in us lie to hinder it; are ready to envie any looke Heaven ward; Doe what in us lye to nip the buddings of grace in the head at its firſt bloſſoming in others; or are wee ſuch as regard not the ſoules of others, let them ſinke or ſwimme. I proclaime from the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven this day, bee they what they will, either Magiſtrate, or Miniſter, or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of a Family; they are not ſincere Converts, and dying in this conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they muſt expect nothing but damnation; for, except they be converted they
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:162306:17"/>ſhall never enter into the Kingdome of Heaven, as our Saviour Chriſt faith, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.3. Except a man be converted, and become as a little child, hee ſhall not enter into the Kingdome of Heaven; So that we muſt looke for a change, or never looke to come in the Kingdome of Heaven. Mee thinks the hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing of this Doctrine ſhould make our bloud runne coole in our veines, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> have never yet to this day regarded our owne ſoules, nor the ſoules of others; that if wee were true Converte our ſelves, wee would indeavour the Converſion of others; but I haſten to a uſe of exhortation.</p>
                  <p>Is it ſo, that converted Chriſtians will indeavour to convert others; Then all you that have taſted of Gods goodneſſe in this particular, in whom the Lord hath wrought this worke of ſaving Converſion; Doe you wonder at the free-grace of God in working this worke of new Creation in you, and give him the glory of it.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, from hence take comfort, that God that ſquares ſinners for his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wne uſe, did not ſquare thee to caſt thee away; but to bring thee to bee uſefull for his glory here; and to glorifie thee hereafter.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, walke as a changed people. And fourthly, indeavour the Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of others, as Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Peter,</hi> When thou art converted, ſtrengthen thy Brethren. Indeavour the Converſion of your new relations, and your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours by praying for them, and mourning over them, and inſtructing of them, though it be not in thy power to change the heart, yet that God that ordinarily workes by meanes, and is found in the uſe of the meanes, hee may be found o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thee in ſuch a way; He can carry home thy inſtructions with power to the ſoul of him, or her thou doeſt inſtruct, and make the meanes effectuall; and though thou canſt doe it but weakly, yet, Who hath deſpiſed the day of ſmall thing. God can worke by the weakeſt meanes; Diſcharge thou thy duty, and leave the ſucceſſe to God, and thou wilt find much comfort, and peace of Conſcience in it.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
